<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: activitylog | AppSmithy]]></title>
  <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/categories/activitylog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-08T01:19:55-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://appsmithy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[AppSmithy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Activity Log Pro released]]></title>
    <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/07/activity-log-pro-released/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-07T23:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/07/activity-log-pro-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first version of <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.appsmithy.activitylogpro">Activity Log Pro</a> Android app is now available! Here&rsquo;s a quick overview of the new features:</p>

<ul>
<li>No Ads!</li>
<li>Calendar view of entries</li>
<li>Export data as an Excel spreadsheet (CSV file)</li>
<li>Automatic backup of data to the cloud</li>
<li>Options for the order in which activities are displayed</li>
<li>Star/favorite activities for easy filtering</li>
<li>Updated UI with Android 4.x look and feel and support for high resolution displays</li>
</ul>


<p>And there are plans to add more in the future! So, do give it a spin!</p>

<h2>Usability improvements</h2>

<p>The Pro version while retaining the flexibility of the free version significantly improves usability in multiple ways. Most signicantly, entries are now also displayed on a monthly calendar to easily visualize the regularity with which an activity is performed. Activities can now be &ldquo;starred&rdquo; with an option to show only Starred activities. This replaces the Archive function found in the free version. There are minor UI improvements all over and the look-and-feel has been updated to be consistent with Android 4.x. The app looks great on the HD displays on our Galaxy Nexus phone and Nexus 7 tablet test devices!</p>

<h2>Behind the scenes</h2>

<p>Android doesn&rsquo;t have a native calendar widget to display data, so we had to roll our own. While it was an interesting exercise, this should be something that the framework should include. On the other hand, implementing automatic backup of the data to the cloud was comparatively straightforward thanks to the almost magical <a href="http://developer.android.com/google/backup/index.html">Android Backup Service</a>. The Backup Service is only available on Android 2.2 and later which means the Pro version isn&rsquo;t available on pre-2.2 devices. Which is not a big deal given that pre-2.2 devices account for less than 1% of the installation base of the free version (which, by the way, works for Android 1.6 and later!). The excellent <a href="http://actionbarsherlock.com/">ActionBarSherlock</a> library made it super-easy to have an action bar that will work for pre-Honeycomb devices. In our opinion, it should be bundled with the <a href="http://developer.android.com/tools/extras/support-library.html">Android support libary</a>!</p>

<h2>Future plans</h2>

<p>While we will continue to support the free version with bugfixes and the ocassional feature addition, the Pro version is almost a new (and better!) app in its own right and we plan to focus on it to make it even better.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building an ad-free version of the Activity Log app]]></title>
    <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/04/building-an-ad-free-version-of-the-activity-log-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T22:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/04/building-an-ad-free-version-of-the-activity-log-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We built <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.appsmithy.activitylog&amp;hl=en">Activity Log</a> primarily to scratch a personal itch. We wanted an app that would help us form good habits by making it easy to be a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantified_Self">Quantified Self</a>. Two years on, our app has gathered a passionate user base that shares our vision for self-improvement. After initial hiccups, the past couple of releases have been bug-free.</p>

<center><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/z7xsxrbivlh3awn/Crashes%20%26%20ANRs%20-%20Activity%20Log.png" height="70%" width="70%" /></center>


<center>Yay! No Bugs!</center>


<p>Although the feature set is sufficient for our personal needs, users have been asking for major new features that would make them even more productive. So that we could provide the best customer experience and support, we decided to build an ad-free version of the app with these features. The question was which features should we build first?</p>

<p>We thought, why don&rsquo;t we ask our current users and prospective customers? So, we asked them what they wanted via an in-app survey. We ran a &ldquo;house ad&rdquo; in the current ad-supported version of the app that linked to the online survey &ndash; you can view or fill it out <a href="http://appsmithy.wufoo.com/forms/activity-log-customer-survey/">here</a>.</p>

<center><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/pjfeenuf2rl7xqu/ActivityLogSurvey.png" height="50%" width="50%" /></center>


<center>In-App Survey as a House Ad</center>


<p>The response rate was quite good &ndash; we heard back from around 3% of our users. Based on the choices that we gave and free-form responses, the prioritized list of requested features became very clear. Here were the top three requested features with the first one being the most asked for by a large margin:
&ndash; Calendar view for entries
&ndash; Export data to a file
&ndash; Store data in cloud for backup and restore</p>

<p>Around 80% of the respondents said they were willing to pay for an ad-free version of the app with these features. That would make the free to paid conversion rate to be around 3% which seems like the going rate for Android apps. Fired up by the amazing response, we started working on the paid version of the app a few weeks ago and we are happy to say it is nearly complete. We are currently beta testing it and hope to announce the release in a few days.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
