<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: log | AppSmithy]]></title>
  <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/categories/log/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-06T00:22:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://appsmithy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[AppSmithy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building an ad-free version of the Activity Log app]]></title>
    <link href="http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/04/building-an-ad-free-version-of-the-activity-log-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T22:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://appsmithy.github.io/blog/2013/07/04/building-an-ad-free-version-of-the-activity-log-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We built <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.appsmithy.activitylog&amp;hl=en">Activity Log</a> primarily to scratch a personal itch. We wanted an app that would help us form good habits by making it easy to be a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantified_Self">Quantified Self</a>. Two years on, our app has gathered a passionate user base that shares our vision for self-improvement. After initial hiccups, the past couple of releases have been bug-free.</p>

<center><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/z7xsxrbivlh3awn/Crashes%20%26%20ANRs%20-%20Activity%20Log.png" height="70%" width="70%" /></center>


<center>Yay! No Bugs!</center>


<p>Although the feature set is sufficient for our personal needs, users have been asking for major new features that would make them even more productive. So that we could provide the best customer experience and support, we decided to build an ad-free version of the app with these features. The question was which features should we build first?</p>

<p>We thought, why don&rsquo;t we ask our current users and prospective customers? So, we asked them what they wanted via an in-app survey. We ran a &ldquo;house ad&rdquo; in the current ad-supported version of the app that linked to the online survey &ndash; you can view or fill it out <a href="http://appsmithy.wufoo.com/forms/activity-log-customer-survey/">here</a>.</p>

<center><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/pjfeenuf2rl7xqu/ActivityLogSurvey.png" height="50%" width="50%" /></center>


<center>In-App Survey as a House Ad</center>


<p>The response rate was quite good &ndash; we heard back from around 3% of our users. Based on the choices that we gave and free-form responses, the prioritized list of requested features became very clear. Here were the top three requested features with the first one being the most asked for by a large margin:
&ndash; Calendar view for entries
&ndash; Export data to a file
&ndash; Store data in cloud for backup and restore</p>

<p>Around 80% of the respondents said they were willing to pay for an ad-free version of the app with these features. That would make the free to paid conversion rate to be around 3% which seems like the going rate for Android apps. Fired up by the amazing response, we started working on the paid version of the app a few weeks ago and we are happy to say it is nearly complete. We are currently beta testing it and hope to announce the release in a few days.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
